const container = document.querySelector('.container');
const questionBox = document.querySelector('.question');
const choicesBox = document.querySelector('.choices');
const nextBtn = document.querySelector('.nextBtn');
const scoreCard = document.querySelector('.scoreCard');
const alert = document.querySelector('.alert');
const startBtn = document.querySelector('.startBtn');
const timer = document.querySelector('.timer');


// Make an array of objects that stores question, choices of question and answer
const quiz = [
    {
        question: "Q. Which of the following is not a CSS box model property?",
        choices: ["margin", "padding", "border-radius", "border-collapse"],
        answer: "border-collapse"
    },
    {
        question: "Q. Which of the following is not a valid way to declare a function in JavaScript?",
        choices: ["function myFunction() {}", " let myFunction = function() {};", "myFunction: function() {}", "const myFunction = () => {};"],
        answer: "myFunction: function() {}"
    },
    {
        question: "Q. Which of the following is not a JavaScript data type?",
        choices: ["string", "boolean", "object", "float"],
        answer: "float"
    },
    {
        question: "Q. What is the purpose of the this keyword in JavaScript?",
        choices: ["It refers to the current function.", "It refers to the current object.", "It refers to the parent object.", " It is used for comments."],
        answer: "It refers to the current object."
    },
    {
        question:"Q.What is the main purpose of the final keyword in Java?",
        choices:["To declare a variable that cannot be changed.","To handle exceptions","To ensure that code is always executed, whether or not an exception is thrown","To indicate that an exception will be thrown"],
        answer: "To ensure that code is always executed, whether or not an exception is thrown"
    },
    {
        question:"Q.Which keyword is used to define a constant in Java?",
        choices:["final","const","static","let"],
        answer:"final"
    },
    {
        question:"Q.Which data structure in Java uses a First-In-First-Out (FIFO) order?",
        choices:["Stack"," Queue","Array","Set"],
        answer:"Queue"
    },
    {
        question:"Q.Which keyword is used to declare a method that doesn't return any value in Java?",
        choices:["void","int","String","double"],
        answer:"void"
    },
    {
        question:"Q.n Java, which access modifier makes a variable or method accessible within the same package?",
        choices:[" public","private","protected","Default (no modifier)"],
        answer:"Default (no modifier)"
    },
    {
        question:"Q.What is the size of the int data type in Java?",
        choices:[" 4 bytes"," 8 bytes"," 2 bytes","It varies depending on the platform"],
        answer:" 4 bytes"
    },
    {
        question:"Q.Which Java keyword is used to create an instance of a class?",
        choices:["new","class","this","super"],
        answer:"new"
    },
    {
        question:"Q.What is the correct way to declare and initialize a String in Java?",
        choices:["String s = Hello","s = Hello","none","both"],
        answer:"String s = Hello"
    },
    {
        question:"Q.Which of the following is not a valid primitive data type in Java?",
        choices:["int","float","double","string"],
        answer:"string"
    },
    {
        question:"Q.In Java, what is the purpose of the break statement within a loop?",
        choices:["To terminate the loop and exit the program","To skip the current iteration and continue with the next iteration of the loop","To indicate that an exception has occurred","To pause the execution of the loop for a specified amount of time"],
        answer:"To skip the current iteration and continue with the next iteration of the loop"
    },
    {
        question:"Q.which of the following of themeselves a collection of different data types?",
        choices:["String","Structure","Char","All of these"],
        answer :"Structure"
    }

    
];

// Making Variables
let currentQuestionIndex = 0;
let score = 0;
let quizOver = false;
let timeLeft = 15;
let timerID = null;

// Arrow Function to Show Questions
const showQuestions = () => {
    const questionDetails = quiz[currentQuestionIndex];
    questionBox.textContent = questionDetails.question;

    choicesBox.textContent = "";
    for (let i = 0; i < questionDetails.choices.length; i++) {
        const currentChoice = questionDetails.choices[i];
        const choiceDiv = document.createElement('div');
        choiceDiv.textContent = currentChoice;
        choiceDiv.classList.add('choice');
        choicesBox.appendChild(choiceDiv);

        choiceDiv.addEventListener('click', () => {
            if (choiceDiv.classList.contains('selected')) {
                choiceDiv.classList.remove('selected');
            }
            else {
                choiceDiv.classList.add('selected');
            }
        });
    }

    if(currentQuestionIndex < quiz.length){
        startTimer();
    }
}

// Function to check answers
const checkAnswer = () => {
    const selectedChoice = document.querySelector('.choice.selected');
    if (selectedChoice.textContent === quiz[currentQuestionIndex].answer) {
        // alert("Correct Answer!");
        displayAlert("Correct Answer!");
        score++;
    }
    else {
        // alert("Wrong answer");
        displayAlert(`Wrong Answer! ${quiz[currentQuestionIndex].answer} is the Correct Answer`);
    }
    timeLeft = 15;
    currentQuestionIndex++;
    if (currentQuestionIndex < quiz.length) {
        showQuestions();
    }
    else {
        stopTimer();
        showScore();
    }
}

// Function to show score
const showScore = () => {
    questionBox.textContent = "";
    choicesBox.textContent = "";
    scoreCard.textContent = `You Scored ${score} out of ${quiz.length}!`;
    displayAlert("You have completed this quiz!");
    nextBtn.textContent = "Play Again";
    quizOver = true;
    timer.style.display = "none";
}

// Function to Show Alert
const displayAlert = (msg) => {
    alert.style.display = "block";
    alert.textContent = msg;
    setTimeout(()=>{
        alert.style.display = "none";
    }, 2000);
}

// Function to Start Timer
const startTimer = () => {
    clearInterval(timerID); // Check for any exist timers
    timer.textContent = timeLeft;

    const countDown = ()=>{
        timeLeft--;
        timer.textContent = timeLeft;
        if(timeLeft === 0){
            const confirmUser = confirm("Time Up!!! Do you want to play the quiz again");
            if(confirmUser){
                timeLeft = 15;
                startQuiz();
            }
            else{
                startBtn.style.display = "block";
                container.style.display = "none";
                return;
            }
        }
    }
    timerID = setInterval(countDown, 1000);
}

// Function to Stop Timer
const stopTimer = () =>{
    clearInterval(timerID);
}

// Function to shuffle question
const shuffleQuestions = () =>{
    for(let i=quiz.length-1; i>0; i--){
        const j = Math.floor(Math.random() * (i+1));
        [quiz[i], quiz[j]] = [quiz[j], quiz[i]];
    }
    currentQuestionIndex = 0;
    showQuestions();
}

// Function to Start Quiz
const startQuiz = () =>{
    timeLeft = 15;
    timer.style.display = "flex";
    shuffleQuestions();
}

// Adding Event Listener to Start Button
startBtn.addEventListener('click', ()=>{
    startBtn.style.display = "none";
    container.style.display = "block";
    startQuiz();
});

nextBtn.addEventListener('click', () => {
    const selectedChoice = document.querySelector('.choice.selected');
    if (!selectedChoice && nextBtn.textContent === "Next") {
        // alert("Select your answer");
        displayAlert("Select your answer");
        return;
    }
    if (quizOver) {
        nextBtn.textContent = "Next";
        scoreCard.textContent = "";
        currentQuestionIndex = 0;
        quizOver = false;
        score = 0;
        startQuiz();
    }
    else {
        checkAnswer();
    }
});